A Finding Aid to the Marian Gore "Art Scene" Interviews and Papers, 1958-1969, in the Archives of American Art AAA.goremari
Archives of American Art
Marian Gore "Art Scene" interviews and papers
1958-1969
AAA.goremari
Archives of American Art
2.2 Linear feet
The Marian Gore "Art Scene" interviews and papers measure 2.2 linear feet and date from 1958 to 1969, with all sound recordings dated between 1962 and 1964. The core of the collection consists of 37 radio programs recorded by Marian Gore for KPFK radio in Los Angeles, California, consisting of interviews with artists, collectors, gallerists, and museum curators. A series of artist files contains notes, correspondence and other materials related to her interview subjects, and a printed materials series contains mainly exhibition posters, programs, and announcements produced by the art spaces with which her subjects were affiliated.
Gore, Marian L.
Existence and Location of Copies note
All of the sound recordings in this collection were digitized for research access in 2010 and are available at the Archives of American Art offices.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in 3 series:
Series 1: "Art Scene" Interviews (1.3 linear feet, Boxes 1-2, 4)
Series 2: Artist Files (0.2 linear feet, Boxes 2, 4)
Series 3: Printed Materials (0.7 linear feet, Boxes 3-4, OV 5)
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated 1997 by Marian Gore.
Biographical/Historical note
Marian L. Gore (1914-2009) volunteered as a radio interviewer for KPFK between 1962-1964, conducting a series of interviews with Los Angeles-area artists, curators, collectors, and gallerists in response to a growing awareness of Los Angeles' rapidly growing role as a creative center and art market.
Born Marian Lucille Moore on Feb. 27, 1914, in Los Angeles to Fred and Lucille Moore. Fred Moore, an attorney, defended Nicola Sacco and Bartolomeo Vanzetti in the infamous 1921 trial. Following her divorce in the early 1960s, Gore approached the radio station KPFK, who was looking for someone to interview local artists. In a 1997 letter that accompanied her donation of the collection to the Archives, Gore writes,
"The early 1960's were an interesting and probably unique period for the Southern California art world. In Los Angeles on La Cienega Boulevard galleries had sprung up like mushrooms, and on Friday nights those who were interested in this scene would go from one gallery to another noting what artists were featured and what trends were apparent. It was a pleasurable way to meet artists as well as a social event where one could see friends and exchange impressions.
"Because I was searching for something to do, at the suggestion of a friend I had gone to radio station KPFK to volunteer my services in any way possible. It turned out to be a most fortuitous time for this offer. The management was interested in possible intervie3ws with artists, and so it all began. I had never done an interview in my life and was astounded to discover how easy it was to get artists, gallery owners, and even museum personnel to talk aobut what they did. Once this began I was swaped with requests for taped interviews, far more than I could manage."
Gore later became an antiquarian bookseller specializing in books on food and drink. She retired in 1994 and donated her book collection to the Los Angeles Public Library.
Scope and Contents note
The Marian Gore "Art Scene" interviews and papers measure 2.2 linear feet and date from 1958 to 1969, with all sound recordings dated between 1962 and 1964. The core of the collection consists of 37 radio programs recorded by Marion Gore for KPFK radio in Los Angeles, California, consisting of interviews with artists, collectors, gallerists, and museum curators. A series of artist files contains notes, correspondence and other materials related to her interview subjects, and a printed materials series contains mainly exhibition posters, programs, and announcements produced by the art spaces with which her subjects were affiliated.
The "Art Scene" Interviews series contains 36 interviews from Gore's "Art Scene" radio series of interviews relating to the contemporary art scene in Los Angeles, particularly galleries and artists showing on La Cienega Boulevard in West Hollywood. Also found is a single episode of another KPFK program called "Seen at the galleries" and hosted by Earl Carter, featuring an interview with Jacques Lipchitz on the occasion of his retrospective at UCLA. Two interviews, with Mathias Goeritz and David Siqueiros, were conducted in Mexico City. Other interview subjects include Michel Albert, Josef Albers, Joan Ankrum, Streeter Blair, Nick Brigante, Robert Cremean, José Luis Cuevas, James Elliott, Claire Falkenstein, Balcomb Greene, Paul Gerchik, Jurgen Hansen, Walter Hopps, Roger Kuntz, Rico Lebrun, Dr. Thomas Leavitt, Jacques Lipchitz, Mario Luna, Robert Mallary, Louise Nevelson, Emilio Ortiz, Esther Robles, Otto Schniede, Fritz Schwaderer, Rufino Tamayo, Esteban Vicente, Robert Wark, and June Wayne.
Artist files include mainly brief, typewritten notes created for Gore's radio interviews, with the questions she asked her interview subjects and brief introductory or concluding remarks. Correspondence is also found in files for Robert Cremean, Iqbal Geoffrey, Balcomb Greene, Robert Mallary, Emilio Ortiz, and Esteban Vicente. Louise Nevelson's file also contains a transcript of her interview with Gore. Also found scattered in some files are notes, photographs, clippings, press releases, resumes, and exhibition programs. Note that not every person in this series has a corresponding sound recording in Series 1, and not every interviewee in Series 1 has a corresponding file in this series.
Most of the material in the Printed Materials series consists of exhibition announcements, programs, and posters from Galleries in the Los Angeles, California area, particularly those along La Cienega Boulevard. Of these, Ankrum Gallery, Ceeje Gallery, Comara Gallery, Dwan Gallery, Ferus Gallery, and Silvan Simone Gallery on Olympic Boulevard contain the most material, with many of the other files containing only one or two pieces. Of note are original prints promoting exhibitions at the Ferus and Ceeje Galleries, and a poster for an art walk along La Cienega Boulevard in the file for the Los Angeles County Museum of Art.
Albers, Josef; Albert, Michel, artist; Ankrum Gallery.; Ankrum, Joan; Blair, Streeter, 1888-1966; Brigante, Nicholas P., 1895-1989; Carter, Earl; Ceeje Gallery.; Comara Gallery.; Cremean, Robert, 1932-; Cuevas, José Luis, 1934-; Dwan Gallery (Los Angeles, Calif.); Elliot, James, 1943-; Falkenstein, Claire, 1908-1997; Ferus Gallery (Los Angeles, Calif.); Geoffrey, J. Iqbal, 1939-; Gerchik, Paul; Goeritz, Mathias, 1915-1990; Greene, Balcomb, 1904-1990; Hansen, Jurgen; Hopps, Walter; KPFK. (Radio staion: Los Angeles, Calif.); Kuntz, Roger, 1926-1975; Leavitt, Thomas W.; Lebrun, Rico, 1900-1964; Lipchitz, Jacques, 1891-1973; Luna, Mario; Mallary, Robert, 1917-1997; Nevelson, Louise, 1899-1988; Ortiz, Emilio, 1936-; Robles, Esther; Schniede, Otto; Schwaderer, Fritz, (Fritz Karl), 1901-; Silvan Simone Gallery.; Siqueiros, David Alfaro; Tamayo, Rufino, 1899-; Vicente, Esteban, 1903-2001; Wark, Robert R.; Wayne, June, 1918-2011; Art--Collectors and collecting--California--Los Angeles; Artists--California--Los Angeles; Curators--California--Los Angeles; Gallery owners--California; Interviews; Photographs; Sound recordings; Transcripts
- "Art Scene" Interviews, 1962-1965; Series 1; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, 4
  Scope and Contents note
  Series contains 37 radio programs created for KPFK radio in Los Angeles, Calif. by Marion L. Gore. Thirty-six of the interviews were part of her "Art Scene" radio series and featured artists, museum curators, art collectors, and gallerists working in the contemporary art scene in Los Angeles, particularly galleries and artists showing on La Cienega Boulevard in West Hollywood. Also found is a single episode of another KPFK program called "Seen at the galleries" and hosted by Earl Carter, featuring an interview with Jacques Lipchitz on the occasion of his retrospective at UCLA.
  Among the many notable California art world figures represented in the collection are Esther Robles, who opened the first gallery on La Cienega Boulevard, who tells the history of her gallery, and Walter Hopps, who discusses the history of the Ferus Gallery and the censorship of the Wallace Berman exhibition there. Interviews with Mathias Goeritz and David Siqueiros were conducted in Mexico City, as was a recording of Gore herself describing the art world of Mexico City. The remainder of interviews were all conducted in Los Angeles.
  Recordings are on 37 sound tape reels. One additional blank reel is also found and has been retained because of annotations on the box. Each reel generally contains one radio program between 15 minutes and a half-hour long. Dates noted are recording dates; broadcast dates were generally within 6 months of the recording dates.
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  All of the sound recordings have been digitized for research access.
  Arrangement note
  Sound recordings are arranged alphabetically by interviewee.
  - Joseph Albers, 1964 June 27; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 1)
  - Michel Albert, 1962 October 23; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 2)
  - Joan Ankrum, 1962 June 7; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 3)
  - Artists' Co-op Gallery, 1962 November 9; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 4)
    Artists who appear in this episode are Alice Pact, Hope Rudolfi, Bob Klick, and John Vincent Mason.
  - Streeter Blair, 1962 August 31; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 5)
  - Nick Brigante and David Sokol, 1962 December 11; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 6)
  - Jose Luis Cuevas, 1962 November 13; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 7)
  - Robert Cremean, 1962 July 2; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 8)
  - Robert Cremean, 1962 November 11; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 9)
  - James Elliot, 1962 July 24; 2 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 10)
  - Claire Falkenstein, 1962 December 4; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 11)
  - Paul Gerchik, 1962 June 22; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 12)
  - Mathias Goeritz, 1964 September 1; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 13)
  - Marian Gore Reporting from Mexico City, circa 1964; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 14)
  - Balcomb Greene, 1963 April 29; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 15)
  - Jorgen Hansen, 1962 July 20; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 16)
  - Walter Hopps, circa 1962; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 17)
  - Virginia Kondratief and Eugenie Klix, 1962 May 25; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 18)
  - Roger Kuntz, 1963 March 6; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 19)
  - Thomas Leavitt, 1962 May 29; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 20)
  - Rico Lebrun
    - Part 1, 1963 January 7; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 21)
    - Part 2, 1963 January 9; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 22)
  - Jacques Lipchitz, 1963 March 8; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 23)
  - Mario Luna, 1962 August 23; 1 sound tape reels 10.5 inch diameter (Box 1, Item 24)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4.
  - Robert Mallary, 1962 June 18; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 25)
  - Douglas McClellan, circa 1962; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 26)
  - Louise Nevelson, 1963 May 21; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 27)
    See Nevelson file in Series 2 for transcript.
  - Emilio Ortiz, 1963 February 14; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 28)
  - Esther Robles, 1962 May 3; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 29)
  - Otto Schneid, 1962 June 26; 1 sound tape reels (Box 1, Item 30)
  - Fritz Schwaderer, 1963 May 26; 1 sound tape reels (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 1)
  - David Siqueiros, 1964 September 1; 1 sound tape reels (Box 2, Folder 1, Item 2)
  - Rufino Tamayo, 1964 November 23; 1 sound tape reels (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 1)
  - Esteban Vicente, 1962 August 25; 1 sound tape reels (Box 2, Folder 2, Item 2)
  - Robert Wark, 1962 April 24; 1 sound tape reels (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 1)
  - June Wayne, 1962 May 28; 1 sound tape reels (Box 2, Folder 3, Item 2)
  - Blank Tape, 1965 January 4; 1 sound tape reels Box is labeled with KPFK label, date, and title "Marian Gore." (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Mario Luna Reel (Box 4)
    Oversized reel from Box 1, item 24.
- Artist Files, 1959-1964; Series 2; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 2, 4
  Series is arranged alphabetically by artist or art world subject. Interviews with the subjects listed in this series are found in Series 1. Exhibition announcements, programs, and posters related to many of the subjects are found in Series 3, Printed Materials.
  Series contains mainly brief, typewritten notes created for Gore's radio interviews, with the questions she asked her interview subjects and brief introductory or concluding remarks. Correspondence is also found in files for Robert Cremean, Iqbal Geoffrey, Balcomb Greene, Robert Mallary, Emilio Ortiz, and Esteban Vicente. Louise Nevelson's file also contains a transcript of her interview with Gore.
  Also found scattered in some files are notes, photographs, clippings, press releases, resumes, and exhibition programs. Note that not every person in this series has a corresponding sound recording in Series 1, and not every interviewee in Series 1 has a corresponding file in this series.
  - Michel Albert, circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Joseph Albers, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Artists' Co-op Gallery, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Oversized material moved to Box 4.
  - Streeter Blair, circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Jose Luis Cuevas, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Robert Cremean, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - James Elliot, circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Claire Falkenstein, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Iqbal Geoffrey, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Paul Gerchik, circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Balcomb Greene, circa 1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Jorgen Hansen, circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Walter Hopps, circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Roger Kuntz, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Rico Lebrun, circa 1963 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Thomas Leavitt, circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Robert Mallary, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Douglas McClellan, circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Louise Nevelson, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Emilio Ortiz, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Gifford and Joann Phillips, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Esther Robles, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Kenneth Ross, circa 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Esteban Vicente, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Robert Wark, circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - June Wayne, 1959; circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Frederick Wight, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Oversized material from Artists' Co-op Gallery (Box 4)
    Oversized material from Box 2, folder 7.
- Printed Materials, 1958-1969; Series 3; 0.7 Linear feet (Boxes 3-4, OV 5)
  Series is arranged alphabetically by the name of the gallery or organization the produced the printed material. An article reproduced from the Texas Quarterly is filed under "Article," and an item with no attribution is filed under "Publicity."
  Most of the material in this series consists of exhibition announcements, programs, and posters from Galleries in the Los Angeles, California area, particularly those along La Cienega Boulevard. Of these, Ankrum Gallery, Ceeje Gallery, Comara Gallery, Dwan Gallery, Ferus Gallery, and Silvan Simone Gallery on Olympic Boulevard contain the most material, with many of the other files containing only one or two pieces.
  Also found are program guides from the radio station that broadcast Gore's interviews, KPFK in Los Angeles, and its sister station, KPKA in Berkeley, California.
  A Bruce Connor poster from Ferus Gallery has handwritten notes on the back. The Los Angeles County Museum of Art folder also contains a poster advertising an art walk on La Cienega Boulevard sponsored by the Museum.
  Of note are original prints promoting exhibitions at the Ferus and Ceeje Galleries, and a poster for an art walk along La Cienega Boulevard in the file for the Los Angeles County Museum of Art.
  - Article, "Painting, Dialectics, and Existentialism" by Paul Laporte, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - American Crayon Company, circa 1961 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Ankrum Gallery, 1960-1962, 1969 and undated (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Ceeje Gallery, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Comara Gallery, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dalzell Hatfield Galleries, 1959, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Dilexi Gallery, circa 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Dwan Gallery, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Overised material moved to OV 5.
  - Ernest Raboff Gallery, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Esther Robles Gallery, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Feingarten Galleries, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Felix Landau Gallery, 1962 and undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Ferus Gallery, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Oversized materials moved to Box 4.
  - Galleria Gianni, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Gallery of Gilles A. de Turenne, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Grand Central Moderns, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Hebrew Union College, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Heritage Gallery, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - KPFK and KFPA Program Guides, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Konstalongen Kavaletten, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Long Beach Jewish Community Center, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1959-1966 and undated (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
    Oversized material moved to OV 5.
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Pasadena Art Museum, 1958, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Paul Plummer Galleries, circa 1965 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Paul Rivas Gallery, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Primus Stuart Galleries, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Publicity, Ruth Asawa, circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Ryder Gallery, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Sabersky Original Prints and Paintings, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Silvan Simone Gallery, 1960-1965 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Watts Towers, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Zora's Gallery, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Oversized printed material from Ankrum Gallery (Box 4)
    Oversized material from Box 3, folder 3.
  - Oversized printed material from Ceeje Gallery (Box 4)
    Oversized material from Box 3, folder 5.
  - Oversized printed material from Ferus Gallery (Box 4)
    Oversized material from Box 3, folder 14.
  - Oversized printed material from Pasadena Art Museum (Box 4)
    Oversized material from Box 3, folder 26.
  - Oversized printed material from Dwan Gallery (Box OV 5)
    Oversized material from Box 3, folder 9.
  - Oversized printed material from Los Angeles County Museum of Art (Box OV 5)
    Oversized material from Box 3, folder 24.
  - Oversized printed material from Silvan Simone Gallery (Box OV 5)
    Oversized material from Box 3, folder 34.